Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adopted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Subscription: liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
Perturbed by the thoughts on my mind
no matter how hard I try to sever my love.
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For all the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For all the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Subscription: liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Peace to you, My Lady.
Where are we?
We are at the side gate of the North Entrance.
The side gate?
Only Her Majesty the Empress can use the main gate.
Meizhuang!
My Lady, you will have time to catch up later.
Your baggage has been delivered to your residence.
Please follow us.
Where does Attendant Sourire live?
The Palace of Pearl Jade.
Farewell, My Lady.
Please follow me, Attendant Sourire.
Please follow me, Companion An.
Please follow me, Lady Shen.
It's splendid! No wonder everyone wants to live in the palace.
My Lady, wild geese is a sign of good luck.
I hope you are excited about your new home.
Peace to you, My Lady.
You may rise.
Thank you, My Lady.
My Lady, this is your residence, Chamber of Brilliance.
Thank you.
Sir, please treat yourself to a cup of tea.
Thank you, My Lady. Please enter.
It's getting gloomy.
Not at all, it's a quiet place.
That will be good for you, My Lady.
My Lady, this is your residence.
Thank you, sir.
Take care.
How did you get in?
What a small palace for enemies!
Huh, a Companion are you?
Companion An, everything's ready in your room.
Greetings, Dongchun.
No.
Don't you address me like a friend!
Peace to Attendant Xia.
Peace to you, Attendant Xia.
That is how you greet me.
My Lady, please come see your room.
This is your palace.
Looks nice. It seems newly renovated.
It was. The palace was assigned to
Lady Parfum after His Majesty's coronation.
So we are living with Lady Parfum?
(hesitates) Please, My Lady.
Attendant Sourire.
Peace to My Lady.
You may rise.
It was a long trip.
Have a good rest, My Lady.
Thank you.
My Lady, I hope you like your palace.
We cleaned it thoroughly this morning.
Palace of Pearl Jade.
I like its name.
My Lady, this is the main chamber.
On its east and west are the side chambers.
Behind it is the bedchamber and a garden.
On the south of the main chamber is your summer residence.
The palace was named for its pear flowers,
which look like falling pieces of jade.
And the crabapple trees bear bright red flowers
and look very festive.
Why is there a stage?
There are many theaters in the palace for the concubines.
This one became less frequented,
so it was built into a residence.
(sidetracks) How do you like the palace, My Lady?
It's very calming.
My Lady, Her Majesty the Empress
had the sweet olive trees planted for you.
She wishes you a sweet life in the palace.
Exactly.
It was very kind of Her Majesty.
Please enter the main chamber, My Lady.
My name is Kang Luhai.
I'm the head eunuch of your palace.
Peace to you, My Lady.
My name is Cui Jinxi.
I'm the head maid of your palace.
May peace be with you.
Please rise.
—Yes.
—Thank you, My Lady.
I was told that Lady Parfum lives here as well.
I should pay respect to her right away.
My Lady, Lady Parfum does not live here any more.
Her west chamber is vacant.
Attendant Chun moved into the east chamber four days ago.
She will visit you later.
My Lady, this is Xiao-Yunzi.
These two are apprentices to Mr. Kang:
Xiao-Hezi and Xiao-Yinzi.
These are your maids: Violet and Daisy.
They are all at your service.
May peace and grace be with you, My Lady.
It was nice to meet every one of you.
I do expect my servants to be smart and efficient.
But what I require is absolute loyalty.
(Yes x3)
Do you understand?
Yes, My Lady.
(whisper) Go ahead.
My Lady, you must be tired from the trip.
Would you like to take a rest?
Yes, you may leave.
Madam Cui, you must have been in the palace for a while.
My Lady, please call me by my humble name—Jinxi.
Madam, please stand.
Please don't be inhibited by the rules.
You are my elder and more experienced in the palace.
I should be respectful to you.
I'm not worthy of your courtesy, My Lady.
I used to serve the concubines of the prior emperor.
It's my pleasure to work for you.
You must be a reliable person for your extended service in the palace.
I'm flattered, My Lady.
Thank you for taking care of my palace with Mr. Kang.
My Lady, I will spare no effort.
Please go have a break.
Vermilion and Jade will take over.
Thank you, My Lady.
(sigh of relief) What a stressful day!
There were a whole lot of rules!
It was so scary.
But the room's so nice.
You must be careful not to break any rules.
You two have to be exceedingly careful as my dowry maids.
For sure!
Vermilion always speaks without thinking.
Get out of here!
It's not that bad. She knows how to talk properly.
We grew up as a family, and moved here together.
Living in the palace is like walking along a cliff with
our eyes covered. We have to trust and help each other.
We are all in the same boat.
You treat us like your sisters.
We will protect you at our best.
I will take good care of you both as well.
Please don't worry, My Lady.
Your Majesty, would you like a break and some tangerines?
The new concubines must have settled in by now.
Yes, everything went well.
I can finally have some time to myself
when Consort Fleur is taking care of the palace.
She's the only thing Your Majesty should worry about.
Song Zhi took away the pomelos and gave us the tangerines.
She claimed that her palace deserves the best
because His Majesty will eat there.
And last time,
when Suzhou Clothing Services supplied textiles,
she got to be the first one to choose.
Not a big deal. Just let her be.
The peonies in the yard need to be taken better care of.
Please inform the gardeners.
But ...
Her Majesty can't be bothered to care about her.
Where's Vermilion?
My Lady, you sent her to bring some pastries
to Lady Shen and Companion An.
The kitchen just finished making the pastries,
and Vermilion is on her way.
My Lady, Madam Autumn sends you housewarming gifts
on behalf of Her Majesty the Empress.
You are required to greet Her Majesty in the Palace of
Great Benevolence at five am after three days.
I understand.
Mr. Zhou from the Palace of Earthly Honors is here.
Palace of Earthly Honors?
That's Consort Fleur's palace.
I see.
- I will be there shortly.
- Aye.
My Lady, Consort Fleur is on a par with Her Majesty.
You cannot show any disrespect.
It's very nice to see you, sir.
Please.
Peace to Attendant Sourire.
Thanks for the wait, Mr. Zhou.
Her Highness Consort Fleur sends you some gifts.
Thank you, and please thank Her Highness for me.
Would you like to sit down for a cup of tea, sir?
I would love to, but I have to visit other concubines.
I'm afraid I have to go now.
Thank you for coming, sir.
I bid you a good day, My Lady.
Congratulations, My Lady.
Her Highness was very generous.
Please make a record of the gifts and keep them in the storeroom.
My Lady, you received as many gifts as Lady Shen.
And Lady Fuca and Attendant Xia
in Companion An's palace.
Consort Fleur must be trying to buy over the new concubines.
Peace to Attendant Xia.
Madam Autumn, you shouldn't have visited personally.
Come on in!
Her Majesty will be happy to know that
you are pleased with everything in the palace.
I hope you like the textiles from Southern Clothing Services.
Thank you and thank Her Majesty.
I am extremely flattered!
You are welcome. Allow me to take my leave.
Take care, Madam.
Goodbye, My Lady.
It is no one else's fault that you were born in a poor family.
(tut) Is that all the gifts you received?
Consort Fleur's gifts are incomparable to Her Majesty's.
Make a dress with the textile in three days.
I will thank Her Majesty in that dress.
Don't listen to her, My Lady.
She wasn't wrong.
My Lady, your background doesn't determine your future.
My Lady, Attendant Chun is here.
Come on in!
You had a busy day, Sourire. Hope I'm not disturbing!
Not at all. I was just about to go visit you.
Have a seat.
Jade, make some tea.
I hope you like Pu'er tea.
You have so many good pastries here.
I lost my appetite at dinner. Can I have some pastries?
I'll have the tea later.
Go ahead!
Vermilion, bring more pastries.
It's so good!
You look very young.
(chewing) No, I'm fourteen.
If you don't like Pu'er ...
Jade, make milk tea.
Thanks, I love sweet food.
Take your time, Attendant Chun.
Please call me Chun'er. That's what my family call me.
Sure.
Was there something wrong with your dinner?
I was missing home.
The Imperial Kitchen made wine-soaked goose,
and my mom is really good at cooking it.
So I felt homesick.
Come eat with me the next time you miss home!
Can I?
You're so nice to me!
His Majesty really likes you.
The yard was packed with people and gifts in the afternoon.
Would you like some flower hairpins?
They would look good on you!
It's okay ... I like the pastries more.
Eat as much as you want.
Jade, wrap up some good ones for Chun'er.
Thank you, Sourire.
(singing)
The Imperial Garden was a feast for the eyes.
What a loose woman!
Are you making an embroidery or a siren song?
You cannot sleep with His Majesty in the first three days.
Just wait till you can sing your way to His Majesty's bed.
I didn't mean anything like that.
I will stop if you don't like it.
Don't give me that face!
I didn't do anything.
Don't you dare seduce His Majesty with that weepy face!
Not on my watch!
Who does she think she is?
My Lady, you must not take her words seriously.
It's fine. I will leave when she's here.
Let's go see how my friends are doing.
Smells good,
doesn't it?
Let's get another one.
Eh, come on in!
You should have announced the arrival of Lady An!
How could you let her wait in the sun?
It's not his fault. I asked him not to.
I didn't want to interrupt, but you were disturbed nonetheless.
It's not your fault.
Huan'er, you scared her.
You owe her an apology.
Sorry, please come in for tea.
I went to Meizhuang's palace first, hoping to
come here with her. But she had already left.
It was good timing. Now it's time for us to catch up!
The head of my palace, Concubine Estime, is very kind and friendly.
How about your palace?
It's not too bad.
Lady Fuca is all right.
But Attendant Xia ...
I will stay away from her.
I will spend more time with you two.
You are always welcome here.
I made herbal tea instead of green tea for you.
After living for a few days at your home,
I troubled Jade to remember all my preferences.
You both treat My Lady as your sister.
I must serve you as best I can.
Jade has a honeyed mouth and a sweet heart.
I'm grateful to have her all these years.
Of course, our dowry maids serve us the best.
I moved in with Lunar and Starry.
Lingrong, you didn't have a dowry maid.
How are the servants in your palace?
Coua is a competent maid. I can always count on her.
The other two are just fifteen years old, not as dependable.
Don't worry, I can take care of myself.
Jinxi!
Yes?
Please inform Her Majesty that
Daisy is sent away to serve Companion An.
Yes.
Daisy is young but well-trained.
I'll let you have her.
Don't hesitate to tell us if you need anything else.
Thank you so much.
The textiles I received today can be made into dresses for you.
Lunar will bring them to your palace later.
I can never repay your kindness.
I will be eternally grateful for your support and help.
We are sisters. We look after one another.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
My Lady, it's your first time to pay respects to Her Majesty today.
You should dress up to stand out.
Please go boil water for me.
Jade will help me get dressed.
Do my hair as usual.
Your Highness, it's time to leave.
We have to be on time today.
There's no hurry.
Your Highness is uniquely stylish.
The phoenix coiffure looks incomparably distinguished.
[Phoenix is the female equivalent to the emperor's dragon]
Let's go.
Thank you for arriving early.
How's everyone doing in the palace?
Very well. I thank Your Majesty.
I hope I'm not late.
Peace to Consort Fleur.
Peace to Your Majesty.
Please rise.
Were you feeling unwell to get up on time?
His Majesty was working late last night,
so I stayed up with him.
And His Majesty told me to sleep in a bit.
I hope it's all right with Your Majesty.
His Majesty has been busy lately.
He should make it up to you.
From now on, you will not be as tired since
His Majesty can stay with the new concubines.
Who is she to show off to Her Majesty?
(Jiang Fuhai)
The new concubines will kneel and bow to Her Majesty.
May grace and peace be with Your Majesty.
All rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
Please greet the other concubines.
Consort Honnête is unwell and absent today.
Her health is not improving.
Autumn, please visit her after the ceremony.
Yes, Your Majesty.
The new concubines will greet Consort Fleur.
Grace and peace to Your Highness.
The jadeite we received this year is overly light in color.
Fine jadeite is becoming rare.
You are too young for dark-colored jadeite.
But I believe that only the finest jadeite
was selected for the imperial family.
Of course, jadeite is not for my age.
I should give my jadeite earrings to Your Majesty if you like.
I recently received a pair of earrings made of eastern pearls.
I should not be extravagant.
His Majesty wouldn't appreciate that either.
I admire your frugality.
Well, they have been kneeling for a while.
Oh, I was too absorbed in the conversation.
Rise.
I thank Your Highness.
I wonder which one is Attendant Xia.
Peace to Your Highness.
I am the Attendant from the Xia family.
You are very well attired.
Your dress must be expensive.
It was made from Her Majesty's gift.
I'm wearing it for this special occasion.
You are a grateful recipient of gifts.
Rise.
I thank Your Highness.
And I wish to meet Lady Shen and Attendant Sourire.
Peace to Your Highness. I am Lady Shen
from the Palace of Universal Happiness.
Peace to Your Highness.
I am Attendant Sourire from the Palace of Pearl Jade.
Lady Shen has an air of elegance.
Attendant Sourire is clearly visible
despite her inconspicuous dress.
His Majesty has a keen eye for beauty.
All right, you may rise.
I thank Your Highness.
Your Highness has the face of a peony.
We are pale as candlelight
when compared to the radiant smile of Your Highness.
That is very sweet of you.
But the phrase "the face of a peony"
isn't it most appropriate for describing the Empress.
Her Majesty is as beautiful as a mudan peony
[mudan is the type of peony that describes the Empress],
while Your Highness has the face of a shaoyao peony.
We are incomparably inferior.
Now we have more sweethearts in the palace.
Every one of you is sweet and smart.
I wish to remind you that your priority in the palace
is to expand the imperial family.
As a family, you must not displease
His Majesty with jealousy or rivalry.
Yes.
Jiang Fuhai, is the Empress Dowager expecting us?
Her Majesty the Empress Dowager sends her regards.
Her Majesty is practicing meditation to pay homage to the Buddha.
I understand.
You may leave now.
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
That was quite a show!
You adulated Consort Fleur right after pleasing the Empress.
Very well played!
How I admire your skills!
Peace to Attendant Xia.
You have a brigade of servants carrying your gifts.
Is there enough space for them in your palace?
The imperial favors should be shared among the entire family.
Would you like to be the first one to choose
since you are already here?
Please have a look.
My family was never short of stuff like this.
But Lady Shen, you are very
good at buying off the concubines.
How could someone like her be selected?
The Xias are not even qualified to carry shoes for our family.
She's been a pain in the neck to Lady Fuca
and giving trouble to Companion An in her palace.
Does she think she can swagger in the palace
wearing that dress from the Empress?
Attendant Xia, I heard that you come from a military family.
My family has long been the warriors of the country,
unlike the magistrate of a village.
I am truly sorry for what happened at the Selection.
I believe Attendant Xia is intellectually and martially
superior raised in a military family.
I was impressed by your manners like a soldier.
Now I understand that it is in honor of your family.
I must live up to your family's teaching.
How could that idiot be an Attendant in the palace?
Did she attend school at all?
Stop! You cannot beat a concubine!
Let go!
Peace to Your Highness.
Your Highness.
—Zhou Ninghai.
—Yes.
It's all right.
I was taking a walk in the Imperial Garden,
only to have my day spoiled by this violent scene.
How disappointing!
Companion An verbally offended me.
I just wanted to discipline her.
No offence meant.
I thought it was my job to discipline the concubines.
When did you take over the palace?
I'm afraid you are unable to shoulder the responsibility.
The maple leaves are not red enough this year.
Your Highness, I heard that the maple trees
can take in blood to add color to their leaves.
Is that so?
I shall reward Attendant Xia with the Scarlet Red.
So that we can add color to the maple leaves.
The Scarlet Red?
My Lady, the Scarlet Red is a penalty in the palace.
Your legs will be beaten with wooden sticks
that are two inches thick and five feet long.
Until there is a scarlet pool of blood on the ground.
So we call it the Scarlet Red.
My Lady, please come with us.
Please spare me, Your Highness.
I will never do it again.
It would be a great honor
if your blood can add color to the imperial trees.
Please spare me, Your Highness.
Take her to the Imperial Department of Penalty.
Xia disrespected her peer concubines.
But the three of you were also involved.
She has learned her lesson, but you cannot get away with it.
Go back to your palace to reflect on how you should behave.
It made my blood run cold.
That was too much of a penalty.
I didn't expect Consort Fleur to treat concubines with such cruelty.
Is she going to punish us?
Don't worry, she simply asked us to go back.
We should go back to our palaces. I'm so scared.
Let's go.
What happened?
What is going on?
There ... There is ...
Calm yourself down.
My Ladies, I was checking the water in garden wells.
But in that well ... I ...
I will take a look.
You shouldn't. He's already scared.
I'll be fine.
What is it?
It's ...
It's a dead body.
Your Majesty, it was Fuzi.
Fuzi?
How could she end up dead in a well?
I have no idea. The well is located in a lonely place.
Fuzi was sent to serve Consort Fleur ...
Rise.
I will go ask Consort Fleur about it.
There's one more thing.
Yes.
Consort Fleur punished Attendant Xia with the Scarlet Red.
That's all right. It was her fault.
I feel sorry that Fuzi died at such a young age.
I couldn't find her anywhere!
Keep looking!
My Lady, where have you been?
We've been looking for you.
Are you feeling unwell, My Lady?
Please sit down.
My Lady, Her Majesty informed the harem that
the new concubines can serve His Majesty after today.
Congratulations, My Lady!
You will be definitely the first one.
Not necessarily tomorrow, My Lady,
but you should always be prepared.
Are you feeling hungry?
Serve lunch quickly.
No.
I'm not hungry.
She needs to rest. She'll have lunch later.
Your Highness, Jiang Fuhai
requests to see you on behalf of the Empress.
- Show him in.
- Yes.
I bow before Your Highness.
Rise.
Mr. Jiang, I was just going to send for you.
Yes.
Is Fuzi someone important? She's got quite an attitude.
Your Highness must be joking. She is just a maid.
Joking?
Excuse my joke if I say Fuzi was disobedient to me
because the Empress has her back.
Fuzi was selected by the Household Department.
She hardly served Her Majesty before coming here.
There's no such thing as "the Empress has her back".
She pulled my hair violently the other day.
I scolded her for that, and she ran away and never returned.
I thought that was how the Empress instructed her maids?
Your Highness, Fuzi is dead.
Dead?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Lonely Phoenix
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
I dimly recall the colorful blooms in every summer.
They are as distant as the autumn moon in the water.
He loved me with a volatile heart.
And before I knew it, we fell apart.
Behind me are the promises and longing.
Before me lie the flute and the zither.
I loved you with my body and soul
But you hurt me from head to toe.
My wish ran athwart
and I ended up a fool of my destiny.
My love was the wind-swept flowers from a tree.
A plum bloomed in Dongchun hoping for a fruitful summer.
But the irresistible winds of destiny destroyed her wish.
You can hear the flapping of a phoenix
but you will never see it.
What you see is the falling leaves from the phoenix tree.
The falling leaves from the phoenix tree.